I am a researcher with over ten years' experience in project coordination and supervision, as well as data management, analysis, and reporting. I am happiest working at the intersection of K-12 education research and data management planning, helping researchers and practitioners obtain insights that improve student outcomes through harmonized, reliable, and documented data. I am also passionate about helping others organize their data and reporting through reproducible workflows.

Technical Skills

R (data wrangling), RMarkdown/Quarto (reporting), Qualtrics, Git and GitHub, SPSS, Microsoft Access, Stata, Quick Base, SQL, SharePoint, Tableau

Education

University of Minnesota

Minneapolis, MN

MASTER OF PUBLIC POLICY

2009-2011

• Concentration: Advanced Policy Analysis

University of Missouri

Columbia, MO

BACHELOR OF SOCIAL WORK

2001-2005

Concentration: Research Methods

Experience

Freelance Remote

DATA MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT

Mar 2022 - Present

• Providing research data management consulting, training, and data wrangling services to improve organizational workflows.

Streamline Data Science

Remote

Data Scientist Nov 2021 - Mar 2022

- Created example client facing customer relationship management dashboard in R flexdashboard to demonstrate services.
- Built Google Trends interactive R flexdashboard to show capabilities of automatic updating data.

Missouri Prevention Science Institute

University of Missouri

DIRECTOR OF DATA STRATEGY

May 2019 - Nov 2021

- Strategized data management plans for over ten externally funded projects and oversaw their implementation.
- Created standard operating procedures for all data management practices and provided annual staff training on systems.
- Merged, cleaned, queried, validated, and documented data collected from school districts, state education agencies, surveys, assessments, and observations using R.

DIRECTOR OF RESEARCH IMPLEMENTATION

Jul 2016-May 2019

- Supervised project staff, ensuring successful completion of data collection activities for six federally funded randomized controlled trial studies and two county funded projects.
- Designed and built data collection tools including Qualtrics surveys and Access tracking databases.
- Built reports, dashboards, and visualizations for dissemination of data.

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE Aug 2013 - Jul 2016

- Coordinated activities for two Institute of Education Sciences funded randomized controlled trial studies.
- Collected data in schools through classroom observations, surveys, and assessments.
- Established trusting relationships with school district partners.

Big Brothers Big Sisters of Eastern Missouri

St. Louis, MO

EVALUATION AND OUTCOMES MANAGER

Jun 2011 - Aug 2013

 Oversaw the collection, analysis, and dissemination of data relating to performance management, outcomes, and stakeholder satisfaction.

Center for Advanced Studies in Child Welfare

University of Minnesota

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Jan 2010 - Jul 2011

• Evaluated the effectiveness of the Hennepin County Attorney's Office truancy intervention program using qualitative and quantitative methods.

December 2023

Humphrey School of Public Affairs

University of Minnesota

TEACHING ASSISTANT Aug 2010 - Dec 2010 • Taught lab sessions of a graduate level introductory statistics course using Stata.

Hennepin-University Partnership

University of Minnesota

GRADUATE ASSISTANT Sep 2009 - May 2010

• Connected County officials with University faculty to develop effective partnerships to improve the community.

POWER Issues in Data Management in Education Research Hub

Remote

Jan 2022 - Present

· Organize and host monthly meetups and presentations on data management topics for a group of researchers and data managers in the field of education.

R-Ladies St. Louis St. Louis, MO

CO-ORGANIZER Aug 2020 - Present

• Organize and host monthly workshops on programming in R.

Center for Open Science Unconference on Open Scholarship Practices in Education

Remote

ADVISORY COMMITTEE MEMBER

Oct 2022 - Mar 2023

• Assisted in planning the 2023 event.

RStudio Conference Washington D.C. **TEACHING ASSISTANT** July 2022

Teaching Assistant for What They Forgot to Teach You About R Workshop.

LaunchCode St. Louis, MO

TEACHING ASSISTANT Jan 2018 - July 2018

• Developed curriculum and taught data analysis once a week for a cohort of 25 women looking to make a career transition.

AmeriCorps St. Louis Education Team

St. Louis, MO

TEAM LEAD Aug 2007 - Aug 2008

• Tutored elementary students, led educational programming, and supervised a team of three tutors.

Data Manager for the Following Grants

Boone County Children Services Fund: The FACE of Boone County, PI: Aaron Thompson, (2020-2024)

Institute of Education Sciences: Enhancing the Capacity of Rural Schools to Identify, Prevent, and Intervene in Youth Mental Health Concerns: The National Center for Rural School Mental Health, PI: Wendy Reinke, (2019-2024) (R305C190014)

Institute of Education Sciences: Efficacy study of Discipline in the Secondary Classroom, PI: Carl Sumi, (2018-2023) (R305A170040)

National Institute of Justice: Evaluation of a principal training program to promote safe & civil schools, PI: Keith Herman, (2017-2021) (2016-CK-BX-0004)

Institute of Education Sciences: Evaluation of a training program to promote effective school leadership, PI: Keith Herman, (2017-2022) (R305A170180)

Institute of Education Sciences: Implementing a comprehensive data-based coordinated System of care for school districts to promote youth academic success and social emotional development: A researcher-practitioner partnership, PI: Wendy Reinke, (2017-2019)

Institute of Education Sciences: Evaluation of a self-monitoring training program for elementary school students, PI: Aaron Thompson, (2015-2019) (R305A150517)

Boone County Children's Services Fund: Boone County Mental Health Coalition County-wide Initiative to Support School-age Youth, PI: Wendy Reinke, (2014-2020).

Institute of Education Sciences: The Classroom Check-Up: Supporting teachers in classroom management using a web-based coaching system, PI: Wendy Reinke, (2013–2018) (R305A130375)

December 2023 2 Institute of Education Sciences: Evaluation of a classroom management training program for middle school teachers, PI: Keith Herman, (2013–2018) (R305A130143)

Institute of Education Sciences: Evaluation of a Video-based Modeling Program to Promote Effective Teacher Classroom Management Practices, PI: Wendy Reinke, (2010-2015) (R305A100342)

Publications

Lewis, C. (2024). Data Management in Large-Scale Education Research. CRC Press.

Cohen, D., Lewis, C.G., Eddy, C.L., Henry, L., Hodgson, C. & Huang, F.L. (2021) In-school and out-of-school suspension: Behavioral and psychological outcomes in a predominately black sample of middle school students. School Psychology Review, School Psychology Review, 52:1, 1-14.

Henry, L., Reinke, W.M., Herman, K.C., Thompson, A.M. & Lewis, C.G. (2020) Motivational interviewing with at-risk students (MARS) mentoring: Addressing the unique mental health needs of students in alternative school placements, School Psychology Review, 50:1, 62-74.

Huang, F., Lewis, C., Cohen, D., Prewett, S., & Herman, K. (2018). Bullying involvement, teacher-student relationships, and psychosocial outcomes. School Psychology Quarterly, 33(2), 223-234.

Lewis, C.G., Herman, K.C., Huang, F.L., Stormont, M., Grossman, C., Eddy, C., & Reinke, W.M. (2017). The utility of single-item readiness screeners in middle school. Journal of School Psychology. 64, 1–16.

Presentations ___

Lewis, C. (2024). Data Cleaning for Data Sharing in R. Upcoming invited training for NCME Annual Meeting, Philadelphia, PA.

Lewis, C. (2023). 10 Common Data Management Mistakes. Data Week, Alaska Region of Fish and Wildlife Service, Online.

Lewis, C. (2023). Cleaning Medical Data in R. R in Medicine conference June 5-9, 2023, Online.

Lewis, C. (2023). Essential Data Management Best Practices and Tools for NIH Compliance Panel Discussion. Center for Open Science, Online.

Lewis, C. (2022). Data Management Workflows for Education Research Studies. Guest lecture given to a graduate research methods class at the University of Houston-Clear Lake, Online.

Lewis, C. (2022). 10 Common Data Management Mistakes. Presented for the Society for the Study of School Psychology, Early Career Foundation, Online.

Lewis, C. (2022). A Comparison of Packages to Generate Codebooks in R. A lightning talk for R-Ladies NYC, Online.

Lewis, C. (2021). Data Management in Large-Scale Education Research. Series of workshops given for Missouri Prevention Science Institute, University of Missouri, Columbia, MO.

Lewis, C. (2019). Cleaning Messy Data in R. Presented at R-Ladies St. Louis Meetup, Washington University in St. Louis.

Lewis, C. (2019). Introduction to R. Guest lecture for LaunchCode CoderGirl Data Analysis track, St. Louis, MO.

Lewis, C. (2018). Survey Says: You can use Tableau to Impact School Climate. Presented at Tableau Fringe Festival APAC, Online.

December 2023 3